Guide to the Bettina Bergery Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- August 2002 Acquisition, circa 1900-circa 1990; 23.76 linear feet (63 boxes) + 1 art
  - Writings by Others
    - Gold, Arthur and Robert Fizdale. The Life of Misia Sert (New York: Knopf, 1980) (Box 39)
      Contains annotations by Bergery
    - Goujon, P. Silhouettes Mantaises (Box 40)
      Presentation inscription from Goujon to Gaston Bergery
    - Laure, Marie. Lettres provençales (Box 40)
    - Laure, Marie. Other writings (Box 40)
    - Waugh, Alex. "The Mizner Years." typescript mimeograph (Box 40)
      With notes by Bergery
  - Printed Material
    - Clippings (Bergery, Bettina and Gaston Bergery), 3 folders (Box 40)
    - Clippings (Bergery, Gaston) (Box 40)
    - Clippings (La Falaise, Loulou de), 2 (Box 40)
    - Clippings (Laure, Marie) (Box 40)
    - Other clippings, 16 (Box 41)
    - Other clippings (Box 42)
    - Unidentified, 11 (Box 42)
    - Scrapbook about Alix Grès (Box 50 (Oversize))
    - Scrapbook about Alix Grès, 2 folders (Box 51 (Oversize))
    - Other scrapbooks, 2 (Box 52 (Oversize))
    - Portfolio, 6 (Box 52 (Oversize))
      Contents: clippings and other printed material
    - Other clippings, 10 (Box 53 (Oversize))
    - Other clippings, 10 (Box 54 (Oversize))
    - Other clippings, 10 (Box 55 (Oversize))
    - Other clippings and magazines, 14 (Box 56 (Oversize))
    - Other clippings and magazines, 7 (Box 57 (Oversize))
    - Unidentified, 4 (Box 57 (Oversize))
  - Personal Papers
    - Address book, late 1940's (Box 42)
    - Address book, 1970 (Box 42)
    - Address books, undated; 9 (Box 43)
    - Address books, 2 (Box 44)
    - Appointment book, 1976 (Box 44)
    - Appointment book, 1977 (Box 44)
    - Biographical information (Box 44)
    - Biographical information (Bergery, Gaston) (Box 44)
    - Funeral book (Bergery, Gaston) (Box 44)
    - Hair (Box 44)
    - Identification documents, 2 (Box 44)
    - "Mosley Speaks: the Voice They Cannot Silence" (1 phonograph record) [33 1/3 rpm], 1963 (Box 70 (Record album storage))
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Obituaries (Box 44)
    - Passports (Box 44)
    - Unidentified (1 phonograph record) [78 rpm], undated (Box 71 (Record album storage))
    - Unidentified (Box 44)
    - Unidentified (Box 45)
  - Photographs
    - Bergery, Bettina, circa 1902-circa 1950s; 8 folders (Box 45)
    - Bergery, Bettina, 1930s-50s; 4 (Box 45)
    - Bergery, Bettina, circa 1960s (Box 45)
    - Bergery, Bettina, circa 1970s (Box 45)
    - Bergery, Bettina, circa 1970s; 2 (Box 46)
    - Bergery, Bettina, 1970s-1980s (Box 46)
    - Bergery, Bettina, 1988 (Box 46)
    - Bergery, Bettina, 1990s (Box 46)
    - Bergery, Bettina, undated (Box 58 (Oversize))
    - Bergery, Bettina and Gaston Bergery, 2 (Box 46)
    - Bergery, Bettina wearing clothes designed by Elsa Schiaparelli (Box 46)
    - Bergery, Bettina and others at Miss Howe's and Miss Marot's School (Thompson, Connecticut) (Box 46)
    - Bergery, Bettina and others. Photograph albums, 2 (Box 46)
    - Bergery, Bettina and others in French Equatorial Africa (Box 46)
    - Bergery, Bettina and others in Soviet Union (Box 46)
    - Bergery, Bettina and others in Soviet Union. Photograph albums, 4 (Box 46)
      2 photographs albums, with photographs formerly laid in
    - Bergery, Bettina and others in Turkey, 19 (Box 47)
    - Bergery, Bettina and others in Turkey, 5 (Box 48)
    - Bergery, Bettina and others in Turkey. Photograph album (Box 48)
    - Bergery, Bettina and others in Turkey. Photograph albums, 4 (Box 58 (Oversize))
      2 photograph albums, with photographs formerly laid in
    - Bergery, Bettina and others in Turkey. Photograph albums, 4 (Box 59 (Oversize))
    - Bergery, Bettina and others in Turkey. Photograph album, 2 (Box 60 (Oversize))
      1 photograph album, with photographs formerly laid in
    - Bergery, Gaston (Box 48)
    - Bergery, Gaston (Box 60 (Oversize))
    - Bergery, Nicholas (Box 60 (Oversize))
    - Bergery family (Box 48)
    - La Falaise, Alain de and La Falaise family, 3 (Box 48)
    - De Lamar, Alice (Box 48)
    - Enrico (Bettina Bergery's pet monkey) (Box 48)
    - Fuller, Anne Jones (Box 49)
    - Jackson, Jean Jones (Box 49)
    - Jackson, Jean Jones and Sanford Jackson (Box 60 (Oversize))
    - John XXIII, Pope (Box 60 (Oversize))
    - Laure, Marie (Box 60 (Oversize))
    - Papen, Franz von (Box 49)
    - Pennero, Paule (Box 49)
    - Prat de Nantouillet, marquis de (Box 49)
    - Schiaparelli, Elsa (Box 61 (Oversize))
    - Sert, Isabelle Roussadana Mdivani (Box 49)
    - Van Leyden, Karin and Ernst Van Leyden (Box 60 (Oversize))
    - Unsorted and unidentified, 4 (Box 49)
    - Unidentified (Box 61 (Oversize))
  - Visual Materials
    - Bernard, Christian. Unidentified drawing (Box 49)
    - Brooks, Romaine. Portrait of Natalie Clifford Barney (reproduction of a painting) (Box 49)
    - Cocteau, Jean. Portrait of Daisy Fellowes (reproduction of a drawing) (Box 49)
    - Unidentified. Bust of an unidentified person (sculpture) (Box 64 (Art))
    - Unidentified. Portraits of Bettina Bergery (Box 49)
    - Unidentified. Portraits of Bettina Bergery, 2 (Box 61 (Oversize))
    - Unidentified. Other drawings and watercolors (Box 49)
    - Unidentified. Other drawings and watercolors (Box 61 (Oversize))
    - Unidentified. Painting (Box 69 (Art))
  - Objects
    - Document case used by Gaston Bergery (Box 62)
    - Comb (Box 62)
    - Box with Pope John XXIII coat of arms (empty) (Box 62)
    - Medals in case. Commemorating Pope John XXIII (Box 62)
    - Box with Louis Vuitton label (Box 63 (Art))
- August 2002 Acquisition Addition, circa 1930s-circa 1990s; 1.25 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of author, and within author alphabetically by title of book.
  Contains correspondence, notes, clippings, and other printed material removed from books owned by Bergery.
  - A-Fl (Box 65)
  - Fu-Ne (Box 66)
  - Ni-Z (Box 67)
- March 2011 Acquisition, circa 1950s-circa 1970s; 0.21 linear feet (0.5 box)
  Gift of Mary M. Thacher, 2011.
  Folders are unarranged.
  - Jullian, Philippe. Les Styles (Paris: Plon, c1961) (Box 68)
    Presentation inscription from Jullian to Bergery
  - Mosley, Diana. A Life of Contrasts (London: Hamish Hamilton, 1977) (Box 68)
  - Schiaparelli, Elsa. Shocking Life (New York: Dutton, 1954) (Box 68)
  - Clippings and other printed material (Box 68)
- Other Acquisitions, circa 1970s; 0.21 linear feet (0.5 box)
  - Clippings and other printed material (Box 68)
    Gift of Mary M. Thacher, 2004